# **Ryan Parman**

Cloud-native engineer with a focus on reliability, scalability, and security for the modern web.

With over 20 years experience across software development, site reliability engineering, and security, Ryan enjoys a blend of strategic and tactical problem-solving, from macro to micro scale. Most interested in deployments and infrastructure, developer tooling, automation, discovering better ways to solve problems, and managing development teams/projects.

## **Summary**

Ryan Parman is a cloud-native engineer with a focus on reliability, scalability, and security for the modern web. As an engineering problem-solver with over 20 years of experience across software development, site reliability engineering, and security, he understands how to listen, learn, adapt, and improve. He was a founding member of the AWS SDK team; patented multifactor-authentication-as-a-service at WePay; helped define the CI, CD, and SRE disciplines at McGraw-Hill Education; came up with the idea of "serverless, event-driven, responsive functions in the cloud" while at Amazon Web Services in 2010 (AWS Lambda); and much, much more. Ryan's aptly-named blog, Flailing Wildly, is where he writes about ideas longer than 280 characters. Ambivert. Curious. Not a coffee drinker.

#### **Technical Skills and Software**

While my experience and personal technical interests are broad, the following list is focused more on my interest in DevTools, DevOps, and SRE roles. I would be happy to share additional experience for other areas upon request.

(Proficiency scale: Low, Med, High, Expert)

- Operating Systems: macOS (Expert), CentOS (High), Amazon Linux (High), Amazon Linux 2 (High), Windows (Med), Ubuntu (Med).
- Standard Software Engineering Toolbox: OOP fundamentals, dependency injection, polymorphism, performance, character encodings, Git, Linux, Makefiles, yum, brew, and other fundamentals (High); memorized algorithms (Low); memorized Big-O notation (Low).
- **Programming Languages:** *Modern* PHP (Expert), Bash (High), Browser JavaScript (High), Node.js JavaScript (High), Golang (Med), Python (Med), Ruby (Low). Interested in learning Swift.
- Cloud Computing: Google Cloud's core infrastructure services (not current), AWS (current; EC2, RDS, S3, CloudFront, SQS, SNS, IAM, STS, CloudWatch Monitoring, CloudWatch Logs + Insights, Lambda, ECS-on-EC2, ECR, API Gateway, Auto-scaling, CloudTrail, Elastic Transcoder, ElastiCache, Route 53, ELB/ALB, ACM, SSM, Parameter Store), AWS SDKs + CLI, Docker.
- **Provisioning:** Terraform (High), Terragrunt (Med), Packer (High), Ansible (Med).

- API & Scalable System Design: Understanding and designing highly-scalable, distributed systems for running web applications and web services. ReST-like web service API design. GraphQL (and N+1) implementations. Understand the difference between a true SOA micro-service vs a "distributed monolith".
- Enterprise Services: Artifactory, JIRA, Confluence, GitHub Enterprise, GitHub.com, Phabricator, Pingdom, New Relic, Datadog, Papertrail, Slack.
- Databases & Key-Value/Document stores: MySQL (Med), Redis (High), PostgreSQL (Low), Memcache (Low)
- Metadata Formats: RDFa, Dublin Core, FOAF, CommonTag, OpenSearch, Swagger/OpenAPI, JSON Schema, JSON, YAML, TOML, XML.

# **Work Experience & Notable Projects**

## McGraw-Hill Education — Seattle, WA

## **Engineering Manager, Site Reliability (October 2018—Present)**

Owned, and was the key decision-maker for the <u>development of a core platform</u> of company-wide, reliability-oriented projects. With our development teams moving toward <u>Full-Cycle Development</u>, our SRE team focused on solving more macro-oriented problems which affected more than 75 decentralized engineering teams across the company. These projects have empowered greater self-service for engineering teams, enabling them to move faster without having to reinvent the wheel.

Many of the following projects got their start in my work as an application engineer for MHE, and carried over into this role.

- ECS-optimized Amazon Linux Base AMI for all Amazon ECS applications. Modified the version vended by AWS to meet Level-2 CIS Guidelines for both Amazon Linux and Docker. Underwent deep collaboration with security, operations, and various business units to ensure strict compliance with requirements. Achieved high levels of opt-in adoption, which gave security and operations orgs higher levels of confidence in the product development teams.
- Prism which is an "executive dashboard" enabling significantly improved visibility into the security and
  operational configurations of our AWS accounts (several dozen). Enables visibility to Engineering
  Managers, Directors, VPs, and the CTO, while also providing clear instructions to app engineers about
  why the configuration is incorrect and what needs to be done to resolve the issue.
- Monitoring-as-Code which leverages Terraform and Python to streamline the process of generating
  and maintaining dashboards and monitors in Datadog and New Relic across a large, heterogeneous
  swath of applications. Trained development teams in adopting "full-cycle" development practices
  where the development team owns day-to-day operations of their services including deployments,
  support, and on-call rotations.

- Formed a leadership group to develop a more rigorous process for developing, patching, vending, and
  maintaining re-usable **Terraform modules** that are used by large numbers of product development
  teams across the company. Standardized their development, contribution, and usage guidelines,
  adopted an Apache-style "incubator" for developing new modules, and adopted a process for
  shipping LTS-style packages of modules.
- Took over engineering management responsibilities for the Site Reliability group in MHE's Seattle
  office. Worked to integrate our office better with the larger, developing SRE practice across all offices.
  Joined the SRE leadership group to help guide and participate in the development of better processes
  around reliability, which we then worked with product development teams to adopt and apply.
- Rebooted our Seattle SRE interview process, with a much higher focus on identifying high-quality engineers with a 70/30 split between software engineering (Dev) and systems engineering (Ops), and who were more leaders than not. Integrated many ideas and leadership principles from my time working at AWS. The previous approach was simply to re-brand IT and System Operations as "DevOps" despite having no "Dev" experience to speak of. Adopted a more integrated, <a href="SRE-style">SRE-style</a> of working alongside development teams, and (mostly) ended the practice of dev teams "tossing things over the fence" to some Ops team in the parts of the org that the Seattle SRE team supported.

#### **Staff Software Engineer (October 2016—October 2018)**

Ryan led the development of multiple tier-1 services as part of the educational content authoring pipeline, leveraging REST, GraphQL, API design, AWS, Amazon ECS, Docker, Terraform, ePubs, and security best practices. Led the technical direction of the projects, socialized them, documented them, and provided ongoing guidance around their design and use.

- A member of the core team developing a newer approach to deploying applications, which leveraged
  continuous integration and continuous delivery. While many applications and processes were built
  around larger deployments occurring every few weeks, this team was charged with developing and
  defining newer processes which allowed deployments that were both more frequent, and more reliable.
- Introduced a more hands-on monitoring style, which enables development teams to be more actively engaged in their own operations instead of relying exclusively on an external, third-party vendor used by other groups in the company. This enabled us to provide significantly-lower MTTR during incidents, and by digging into application-level metrics (instead of exclusively infrastructure-level metrics), we were better able to provide valuable data which addressed KPIs/SLOs for the kinds of experiences our customers were having.
- A member of the core team that was migrating all new infrastructure to "Infrastructure-as-Code" tooling such as Terraform, Packer, etc. Identified patterns across applications, and began the effort to streamline infrastructure maintenance with shared, re-usable Terraform modules.

### **Perimeter of Wisdom, LLC**

### Co-Owner, CTO, Producer (February 2015—2018)

On the technical side, Ryan built the entire <u>The First-Time Offender's Guide to Freedom</u> website, soup to nuts. Ryan also produced the eBook, authored by E. M. Baird.

- Leveraged modern tools to build the front-end, including Bootstrap, LESS, JavaScript, Gulp.js, npm, Bower. Ryan built the back-end in PHP 5.6, using HHVM and Nginx, MySQL, Redis, Slim Framework, Monolog, Pimple, Twig, Guzzle, Doctrine, Phinx, and Symfony components. Ryan deployed the application using Ansible, and developed the application in a Vagrant environment running Ubuntu.
- Runs the unit, integration and functional tests using PHPUnit, Behat, Mink, and Selenium. Ryan leverages Amazon SES for sending email, Amazon S3 for static file storage, Stripe for payment processing, Linode for web hosting, MaxMind IP-based geolocation, and Google Books and Dropbox for ensuring that customers always have the latest errata fixes.

### WePay — Redwood City, CA

### **DevOps Engineer (April 2015—September 2016)**

- Improved how WePay provisioned cloud infrastructure, deployed updates, managed security patches, monitored applications and infrastructure, and streamlined the process of planning, developing, deploying and maintaining new micro-services throughout the company.
- Led the cross-company effort to upgrade the monolithic application's software stack from PHP 5.4 to PHP 5.6. This required cross-team collaboration across all of the major engineering teams, QA, and replacing over 200 servers across multiple environments with zero customer-facing downtime.
- Maintainer of multiple tier-1 systems including Artifactory, GitHub Enterprise, Toran Proxy and Phabricator.

#### Senior API Engineer (April 2014—April 2015)

- Developed new API endpoints to help expand WePay's business and support its partners.
- Was instrumental in designing/developing WePay's MFA-as-a-Service offering (<u>"System and Methods</u> for User Authentication across Multiple Domains" (US15042104; Pending)).
- Heavily involved in the security of WePay's products, coordinating fixes with teams against other priorities, and fixing the issues himself in many cases.

### **Amazon** — Seattle, WA

#### Web Development Engineer II, Amazon Web Services (March 2010—April 2014)

- Adapted CloudFusion into the <u>AWS SDK for PHP</u> AWS's SDK for rapidly building cloud-based web
  applications (launched September 2010). Invested heavily in supporting the needs of developers by
  taking the time to listen and understand the needs of developers, and is involved in PHP-related
  industry groups on behalf of AWS.
- Worked with the <u>AWS Elastic Beanstalk</u> team to provide PHP support for the platform (launched March 2012). In addition to working with the PHP community to determine the configuration for a PHP container that would fit the greatest number of developers, he developed a rigorous internal test suite for testing containers which has been used as the basis for testing by other language-specific teams. He also had early input on adding support for git push deployments.
- Heavily involved in the creation and development of the <u>AWS SDK for PHP 2</u>, which takes into account the numerous changes in the PHP language and community since Tarzan/CloudFusion was first written in 2005 (launched November 2012).
- Worked with the AWS Design team on the <u>AWS Management Console</u>, where he lends his experience
  as a web developer and software engineer to bridge the gap between the design and engineering
  disciplines in an effort to build a high-quality, robust, user-friendly console for interacting with Amazon
  Web Services.

#### **Truncated**

Earlier experience is available upon request.

## **Groups & Accomplishments**

- Voting Representative for AWS, PHP Framework Interoperability Group (2012–2013)
- Member, RSS Advisory Board (2007—2009)
- Patent, "Hive-based Peer-to-Peer Network" (US8103870B2)
- Patent, <u>"System and Methods for User Authentication across Multiple Domains"</u> (US15042104; Pending)
- Student guest speaker for the 2004 Silicon Valley College graduation ceremony.

## **Education**

# <u>Carrington College California</u> (née Silicon Valley College) — San Jose, CA

- Bachelor of Arts, Design and Visualization, November 2003. 3.84 GPA
- Related Coursework: Web, graphic, multimedia, and publication design.